Sai Puneeth Chinnam

chinnam.saipuneeth@gmail.com |https://puneeth-chinnam.github.io/Portfolio/ | https://www.linkedin.com/in/puneethchinnam/

SUMMARY

Data Analyst with a master's in Data Analytics Engineering and 3 years of experience across Banking and Supply Chain sectors. Experience in performing Customer Analytics, Automating processes, and Forecasting. Expertise in trend identification from large datasets and dashboard creation.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: SQL, Python, R **Database:** MySQL, Oracle, RDS

BI Tools: Tableau, Power BI, Looker, Microsoft Excel

Cloud Technologies: AWS (Athena, QuickSight, Glue, RedShift, Lambda)

Certifications: AWS Cloud Practitioner, Big Data Analytics – IBM

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Analytics Coop – Supply Chain Logistics

10/2022 - 01/2023

Schneider Electric, Franklin, TN

- Reduced daily report generation time by 70% by implementing ETL data pipelines for sales managers using AWS Glue, integrating S3 buckets and Tableau
- Developed a Python application integrating cross-functional teams' big data pipeline to automate the allocation of Orders and Inventory, reducing 96% human hours
- Forecasted the Bill of Lading (BOL) using the Seasonal ARIMA and Prophet statistical models on time series data with 87% accuracy for the subsequent quarter
- Decreased the Forecast BIAS by 2% using hypothesis testing(t-test) and Error analysis
- Led order retrieval from SAP transactions using SQL queries, cleaned data with macros using VBA, improving data access and processing time

Data Analyst – Advanced Customer Analytics

06/2019 - 07/2021

Cognizant Technology Solutions, Bangalore, INDIA

- Performed analysis to evaluate customer data, validate hypotheses, and measure impact, resulting in improvement in CSAT, Churn Rate, and Contact Rate by 18% quarterly
- Conducted over 10 ad hoc deep-dive analyses on underperforming KPI metrics to identify, produce insights and presented to stakeholders using Tableau on the RDS instance
- Assisted credit analytics team in analyzing Delinquency Rate, DTI, and Credit Score metrics to improve credit models and risk rating system's accuracy, saving 300k dollars over a year
- Owned data collection and processing of the Qualitative metrics, and BPI metrics data on Excel
 employing V-Lookup, Pivot tables, and Conditional formatting features
- Created unified reports and drill-down dashboards in Tableau, created data-oriented analyses and presented to senior leadership and external stakeholders to analyze business performance

Data Analyst Intern - Sustainability Analytics

01/2019 - 05/2021

Cognizant Technology Solutions, Hyderabad, INDIA

- Compiled **exploratory data analyses** and estimated irrigation requirements for crops, utilizing historical data from sensors in agricultural fields, **reducing water consumption by 28**%
- Improved a supervised learning model accuracy for consideration parameters such as water stress index, pH, and temperature, resulting in a 30% increase in agricultural productivity
- Generated dashboards using Power BI for deliverables, effectively visualizing the predictions and providing quantitative findings for stakeholders and business partners

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Data Visualization Project - Covid-19 Impact on NYC Transit - Link

- Compiled 20 data sets for subways and buses from the official MTA website, ride-hailing services data from the NYC TLC, and obtained air quality data from the US EPA data source
- Constructed four **data narratives** on **ridership trends**, the surge in food delivery, traffic volume and emissions, and the prevalence of electric vehicles on the road
- Designed an **interactive dashboard** comprising three page views featuring **14 visualizations** incorporating moving averages, parameters, annotations, and **custom-calculated fields**

Machine Learning Project - Energy Consumption Prediction - Link

- Analyzed energy consumption patterns in buildings using 40 million data points, employing advanced predictive analytics. Conducted feature engineering to identify the critical factors
- Enforced regression analyses using eXtreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost), CatBoost, and Linear Regression Models and tuned hyperparameters, achieving an RMSLE of 1.2
- Developed a presentation illustrating the effectiveness of **sustainable techniques** rooted in environmental factors, resulting in a **25% reduction in energy consumption**

EDUCATION

Master of Science, Data Analytics Engineering

Northeastern University, Boston, MA

Coursework: Data Mining, Statistics in R, Data Visualization, AWS, Database Management

Bachelor of Technology, Electronics and Computer Science

Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University, Hyderabad, India

Coursework: Big Data Analytics, Business Intelligence, Relational data base, Probability and Statistics